A Guide to the Rockefeller family Associates, Berent Friele papers FA468
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller family Associates, Berent Friele papers
1947-1985
Rockefeller Archive Center
Friele, Berent
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich) (1908-1979)
Rockefeller, David (1915-2017)
FA468
7.69 Cubic Feet 19 letter document boxes, 1 legal document box.
20 document boxes. Box 20 is legal size.
Scope and Contents note
The majority of this collection concerns Berent Friele's professional involvement in bettering relations between the United States and Brazil as an advisor on Latin America to Nelson A. Rockefeller during his tenure as governor of New York and later as U.S. Vice President. The collection also documents some of Friele's activities pertaining to or on behalf of David Rockefeller, focusing primarily on Latin America.
Biographical/Historical note
Berent Friele (1895-1985) was the son of the co-owner of Friele & Sons of Bergen, Norway, which was one of the leading coffee trading companies at that time. After finishing school in 1912, Friele went to Hamburg, Germany, to work in for another coffee company. During the World War I, Friele moved to Brazil and continued working for the German coffee company, eventually forming his own company in Santos. While working in Brazil, Friele developed his expertise in the cultivation of coffee and further developed his knowledge of the international coffee trade. In 1918 Friele came into contact with The Great Atlantic and Pacific Tea Company (A&P), which contracted him to perform coffee purchases for the corporation; Friele would later form the American Coffee Corporation (ACC) as a subsidiary company of A&P in 1919. In 1920 Friele married Jenny Muller-Camps (1897-1985) in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. By 1929 Friele had moved up within the ranks to become president of A&P.
Berent Friele was instrumental in strengthening ties between the United States and Latin America, particularly Brazil. In 1934 he was named president of the American Brazilian Association and used his intimate knowledge of Latin America to advise U.S. policymakers on outreach with Latin American countries. In 1940 he served under Nelson A. Rockefeller in the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs (OCIAA), marking the beginning of a lifelong collaboration. The primary mission of the OCIAA was to minimize German influence in Latin America while strengthening U.S. ties with the region, in which both Berent Friele and Nelson Rockefeller played major roles. When Nelson Rockefeller was elected governor of New York in 1958, he appointed Friele his adviser on international relations, a position he retained when during Rockefeller's tenure as as Vice President of the United States.
Arrangement note
The Berent Friele papers are arranged in five series:
Series 1: Biographical Materials. Series 2: General Correspondence. Series 3: Nelson Rockefeller Correspondence. Series 4: Business, Corporate, and Political Files. Series 5: Photographs.
Folders are arranged alphabetically while documents within folders remain in their original order, arranged primarily in reverse-chronological order.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
- Biographical Materials, 1; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Documents and files of a personal nature belonging and pertaining to Berent Friele.
  - ACCION International/AITEC Award Dinner, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Contains an assortment of documents, letters, and bulletins relating to an awards dinner in which Berent Friele was honored with the Distinguished Service Medal by Vice President Nelson Rockefeller.
  - Berent Friele and ACCION, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Further correspondence, bulletins, and photographs relating to ACCION's awards dinner held in honor of Berent Friele. Includes several color photographs of Berent Friele accepting award as well as newspaper clippings of the event.
  - Berent Friele and ACCION: Photographs, 1976 (Box 19, Folder 251)
    Separated Materials
    Photographs have been physically separated from the original file, and relocated to their own folder.
  - Berent Friele Obituaries, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Contains the documents describing the death and last years of Berent Friele's life, including his accomplishments and newspaper clippings.
  - Berent Friele Obituaries: Photographs, 1985 (Box 19, Folder 252)
  - Berent Friele Service Award and David Rockefeller, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Correspondence involving both Berent Friele and David Rockefeller regarding Berent's acceptance of the Distinguished Service Medal from ACCION.
  - Brazilian-American Chamber of Commerce Luncheon, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Pamphlets, correspondence, and records of remarks made at a luncheon held by the Brazilian-American Chamber of Commerce in honor of Berent Friele.
  - Copies of Speeches, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    A compilation of speeches by Berent Friele at a variety of dinners and events hosted by a multitude of organizations.
- General Correspondence, 2; 2.28 Cubic Feet 6 letter document boxes
  A compilation of correspondence and letters sent between Berent Friele and his many colleagues, peers, and associates.
  - ACCION and David Rockefeller, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Correspondence and speeches regarding a dinner held by ACCION in honor of David Rockefeller for his contributions to inter-American relations.
  - American Institute for Free Labor (AIFLD) and David Rockefeller, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Letter correspondence with David Rockefeller regarding the AIFLD.
  - Ambassador Letter, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Letter written to Brazilian Ambassador J.B. Pinheiro by Friele which expressing David Rockefeller's delight at being briefed on current relations between the US and Brazil.
  - Americas Foundation and David Rockefeller, 1977-1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Correspondence regarding the activities of the Americas Foundation involving David Rockefeller. Includes invitation to an Americas Foundation Event.
  - Berent Friele and David Rockefeller, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Correspondence by David Rockefeller with Berent Friele BCC'd.
  - Berent Friele, David Rockefeller, and Assis Chateaubriand, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Correspondence between Berent Friele and David Rockefeller regarding their mutual associate, Assis Chateaubriand.
  - Berent Friele papers, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    An assortment of letters and papers primarily written in Norwegian which are correspondence between Berent Friele and one Mr. Rieber of Norway.
  - Brazilian Embassy Correspondence and Official Notes, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Many letters written both to and by Friele, generally in communication with associates working in the Brazilian embassy. Includes letters referencing Brazil's nuclear program. Includes newspaper clippings and address by Brazilian Ambassador J.B. Pinheiro.
  - Brazilian-New England Conference, 1956-1959 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Press, correspondence, and speeches regarding a Brazilian-New England conference hosted to promote trade and relations between the two areas. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - Christmas Correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    A list of people with which Berent Friele had correspondence of well-wishing during the holiday season.
  - Christmas Correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    An assortment of correspondence pertaining to Christmas well-wishing.
  - Christmas Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Christmas Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Chronological Files, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Contains a multitude of correspondence between Berent Friele and his associates ranging from business to personal in nature.
  - Chronological Files, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Chronological Files, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Chronological Files, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Chronological Files, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Claude C. Erb, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Correspondence between Berent Friele and Claude C. Erb, a Ph.D student who wrote his dissertation on Nelson Rockefeller and his involvement in bettering US-Latin American relations.
  - Claude Erb and David Rockefeller Correspondence, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    An assortment of letters and correspondence most often between David Rockefeller and Claude Erb, but also including Berent Friele.
  - Correspondence and Speech, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Includes a speech made by Nelson Rockefeller which was copied and sent to an editor associate of Friele for use as a citation in an article published by the University of Pittsburgh Press along with further general correspondence.
  - Correspondence L, 1962-1970 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Includes further correspondence of Berent Friele with many different associates with last names beginning with L, most notably a letter which he sent to General Charles A. Lindbergh. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - Correspondence F-I, 1959-1969 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Includes further correspondence of Berent Friele with many different associates with last names beginning with F-I.
  - Correspondence on Business, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Hand-written letters regarding business and investment opportunities in which Berent Friele was involved. Letters sent between Consul General of Denmark and Laurance S. Rockefeller discussing recent visit of Danish royalty to Virgin Islands.
  - Correspondence on Travels and Brazil, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Includes letter from TAP (Airline of Portugal) written to Friele thanking him for a letter he sent of his favorable evaluation of the airline. Most letters concern travels of Friele and his wife, Jenny. Also notable, a correspondence between Friele and one Morgan Trott of San Antonio, Texas writing about their mutual enthusiasm for the idea of the Pan-American Highway.
  - Correspondence with Brazil, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Several letters, some in Brazilian Portuguese, written between Friele and Brazilian dignitaries. Includes postcards.
  - Correspondence with Dr. Janio, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Includes well-wishing and letters written between one Dr. Janio and Friele.
  - Correspondence with Friends, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Assortment of letters with friends and colleagues ranging from well-wishing to business matters.
  - Council on Foreign Relations, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Correspondence regarding meeting with notable Brazilian judges, economists, and politicians. Also a cordial invitation to a summit regarding international oil politics of which Berent is a council member.
  - Council on Foreign Relations, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Correspondence and information relating to one Marcus Vinicius Pratini de Moraes, a Brazilian minister, and his association with Berent Friele. Many invitations to dinner in honor of the Brazilian minister which Berent Friele presided over.
  - Cuba, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Includes long newspaper in style of letter condemning Fidel Castro for his communist regime in Cuba as well as statement announcing creation of Latin American Employment Information Office for Cuban refugees. Contains newspaper clippings and pamphlets.
  - David Rockefeller, 1966-1975 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    Contains photographs of the Consul General of Brazil in New York, Carlos Jacyntho de Barros, presenting David Rockefeller the insignia of a Grand Officer of the National Order of the Southern Cross of Brazil. Also includes correspondence between Berent Friele and David Rockefeller.
  - David Rockefeller Correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    Letters, memos, and messages relating to US-Brazilian relations, generally written from Friele to David Rockefeller although not exclusively. Includes letter from Friele to Rockefeller discussing one Augusto Antunes, a wealthy Brazilian private citizen who was in cooperation with them in improving the infrastructure of Brazil. Includes pamphlet on responsibility of American businesses by Chase. Also includes newspaper clipping on Brazilian use of nuclear energy.
  - David Rockefeller Letter, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    Letter from David Rockefeller to Berent Friele thanking him for a message previously sent by the latter to the former.
  - Department of State Correspondence, 1970-1980 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Many letters discussing US state relations with Brazil, primarily from Friele's point-of-view. Also includes newspaper clippings regarding state of US-Brazilian relations, especially concerning nuclear issues.
  - Dinner in Honor of Galo Plaza, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    A variety of documents, correspondences, invitations, guest lists, itineraries, and letters relating to a dinner being held in honor of Ecuadorian President Galo Plaza by the OAS. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - "E" Correspondence, 1958-1969 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Letters and messages passed between Berent Friele and his associates with last names beginning with E. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - Frank Nattier, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    Correspondence between Berent Friele and Frank Nattier, an associate of Friele's active in the Office of Inter-American Affairs. Primarily concerns plans for a reunion of people involved in the office. Contains invitations as well as a postcard.
  - Friele and David Rockefeller, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    Letters to David Rockefeller about oncoming regime change in Brazil including new president.
  - Friele Letters, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    Letters regarding funding by the Rockefeller Foundation for the Cultura Artistica.
  - Friele Letters, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    Friele correspondence. Pamphlet for Brazilian Symphony Orchestra attended by Friele. Argentinian Ambassador Jorge Aja Espil.
  - "G" Correspondence, 1957-1969 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Letters and messages passed between Berent Friele and his associates with last names beginning with G. Also includes photographs of a newly unveiled statue of Jose Marti sculpted by one Anna Hyatt Huntington.
  - "G" Correspondence: Photographs, 1957-1969 (Box 19, Folder 253)
  - Galo Plaza and OAS, 1967-1973 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    Various letters of correspondence between Berent Friele and Galo Plaza as well as documents pertaining to the OAS.
  - Glazo Plaza and OAS, 1967-1973 (Box 3, Folder 49A)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted from access - personal and confidential.
  - Galo Plaza Correspondence, 1975-1979 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    General correspondence between Berent Friele and Galo Plaza of Ecuador. Includes postcards and several copies of a long memorandum by Plaza titled "The New Crisis in the Hemisphere and How It Can Benefit the OAS" (Organization of American States).
  - General Correspondence A-B, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    A variety of personal and business correspondence comprised of interactions between Berent Friele and associates with last names beginning with letters A-B. Includes newspaper clippings. Includes correspondence relating to IBEC.
  - General Correspondence C-D, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    A variety of personal and business correspondence comprised of interactions between Berent Friele and associates with last names beginning with letters C-D. Includes correspondence regarding a potential order of fishing vessels for IBEC and other documents involving trade as well as a proposal to fund a non-profit medical center. Contains newspaper articles.
  - General Correspondence E-K, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    A variety of personal and business correspondence comprised of interactions between Berent Friele and associates with last names beginning with letters E-K. Includes some correspondence regarding the International Basic Economy Corporation. Includes newspaper clippings. Also includes a large report by the Kraft Foods Company on increasing dairy production.
  - General Correspondence L, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    A variety of personal and business correspondence comprised of interactions between Berent Friele and associates with last names beginning with the letter L. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - General Correspondence M-N, 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    A variety of personal and business correspondence comprised of interactions between Berent Friele and associates with last names beginning with letters M-N. Includes a receipt ticket for a sweepstakes and newspaper clippings.
  - General Correspondence O-R, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    A variety of personal and business correspondence comprised of interactions between Berent Friele and associates with last names beginning with letters O-R, primarily of a business nature. Contains newspaper clippings and an invitation to a meeting of the Rockefeller Center Luncheon Club.
  - General Correspondence S-Z, 1950-1952 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    A variety of personal and business correspondence comprised of interactions between Berent Friele and associates with last names beginning with letters S-Z. Notably includes a memorandum from an annual meeting of stockholders for The Standard Oil Company. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - General Correspondence with David Rockefeller, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    A letter to David Rockefeller with an attached memorandum sent to Nelson Rockefeller regarding Moreira Salles, a successful Brazilian banker working with Nelson to strengthen the Brazilian financial sector.
  - Governor's Committee for International Official Visitors, 1961-1968 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    A large amount of correspondence and documents pertaining to foreign delegations to the United States, the preparations being made for them, and their itineraries.
  - Guillermo Belt, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    Correspondence between Berent Friele and one Guillermo Belt in regards to their mutual acquaintance in Ecuadorian President Galo Plaza. Includes resume of Guillermo Belt.
  - Nelson Rockefeller Correspondence, 1952-1964 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    Personal correspondence with Nelson Rockefeller.
  - Nelson Rockefeller Correspondence, 1952-1964 (Box 5, Folder 61a)
    Restricted from access. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from access.
  - Herberto Lanteri, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    Correspondence with one Herberto Lanteri of the Camara de Exportadores, and organization lobbying for better trade regulations between the US and Latin America, specifically Argentina.
  - Inauguration of Brasilia, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    Press, correspondence, and pamphlets with a focus on the unveiling of Brasilia, the new Brazilian capital. Contains newspaper clippings and a large program created for the inauguration of Brasilia written in Brazilian Portuguese.
  - International Basic Economy Corporation and Other Letters, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    An assortment of letters written by Berent Friele usually in correspondence with associates from his time spent working with many organizations related to Latin America, most notably Brazil. Letter from Berent Friele's nephew about Bergen, Norway, their ancestral home.
  - John Pepion, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 65)
    A detailed resume and curriculum vitae of one John Pepion, including letters of reference and correspondence and detailed work history.
  - Joseph Simonson, 1973-1976 (Box 5, Folder 66)
    Correspondence with former Ambassador to Ethiopia Joseph Simonson regarding the Norwegian-American museum in Decorah, Iowa. Includes pamphlets and photographs of museum.
  - Juanita de Falcon Briceno, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 67)
    Contains correspondence about or from Juanita de Falcon Briceno, wife of a former Venezuelan ambassador to the United States.
  - Juscelino Kubitschek, 1956-1969 (Box 5, Folder 68)
    Contains correspondence between Berent Friele and former Brazilian President Juscelino Kubitschek. Also contains newspaper clippings and other information on Kubitschek.
  - King Olav V, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 69)
    Contains correspondence and newspaper clippings related to and concerning the visit of King Olav V of Norway to the United States.
  - Kissinger and David Rockefeller, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 70)
    Contains a letter sent from Friele to David Rockefeller concerning the political situation in Brazil and the current "cool" relations between the US and Brazil. Also includes his own recommendations to Kissinger on how to better those relations.
  - Laurance S. Rockefeller and "Frederick Billings" Correspondence, 1966-1979 (Box 5, Folder 71)
    Contains correspondence regarding the reconstruction of a ship known as the "Frederick Billings" for use in a museum as a project of the United State Department of the Interior National Park Service. Contains many letters written in Danish.
  - Laurance S. Rockefeller and King Olav Luncheon, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 72)
    Correspondence and news press regarding the visit of King Olav V of Norway to the US as well as a luncheon in his honor. Contains newspaper clippings and postcards. Also contains short pamphlet titled Wings Club Bulletin which focuses on the world of aviation as well as the visit of the King of Norway.
  - Laurance S. Rockefeller and King Olav Visit, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 73)
    Contains further correspondence regarding the visit of King Olav V of Norway to the US as well as details of a luncheon held in honor of the king to which Berent Friele was invited. Also contains letters regarding a plaque unveiling controversy which coincided with the sesquicentennial of a Norwegian presence in the United States.
  - Lisa Von Friedberg, 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 74)
    Contains correspondence between Berent Friele and one Lisa Von Friedberg whose son was put in jail in Venezuela and was requesting assistance from Nelson Rockefeller in freeing him.
  - "M" Correspondence, 1958-1970 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    Letters and messages passed between Berent Friele and his associates with last names beginning with M. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Mesbla S.A., 1955-1966 (Box 5, Folder 76)
    Correspondence regarding Mesbla S.A., a chain of department stores which existed in Brazil from 1912-1999. Contains a large pamphlet in Portuguese discussing the goals and achievements of Mesbla S.A.
  - Michael Rockefeller, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 77)
    Contains copies of newspaper clippings on search for Michael Rockefeller.
  - Michael Rockefeller, 1970-1979 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restricted material.
  - Minister Joao Leitao de Abreu, 1977-1981 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    Correspondence between Berent Friele and Brazilian Supreme Court Justice Joao Leitao de Abreu. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - Miscellaneous Lists, 1950-1952 (Box 6, Folder 80)
    Contains a large assortment of lists ranging from addresses of businesses and people to guests expected to attend certain events.
  - Nelson A. Rockefeller Center for Social Science, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 81)